Guide to the Dallas Shirley papers, 1950-1982 MS0217.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Dallas Shirley collection
1950-1982
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Shirley, Dallas
MS0217.UA
24 Linear Feet
J. Dallas Shirley (1913-1994) graduated from George Washington University in 1936, where he was a member of the basketball team. He received a Distinguished Alumni Achievement award from GW in 1981, and was elected to the Basketball Hall of Fame in 1980. Collection includes plaques, scrapbooks, assorted carved figurines, trophies, pennants and patches, photographs and slides (including Hall of Fame, Red Auerbach), Rome Olymmpics files, media guides officials manuals, Dallas Shirley's diploma, 1936 brick from the "Tin Tabernacle" gym, travel bags, clocks, and books and guides. The collection spans the 1950s through the 1980s.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated to University Archives by Dallas Shirley in 1994.
Biographical Note
J. Dallas Shirley (1913-1994) graduated from George Washington University in 1936, where he was a member of the basketball team. He received a Distinguished Alumni Achievement award from GW in 1981, and was elected to the Basketball Hall of Fame in 1980. Dallas Shirley was known worldwide as an authority on basketball rules, and ranks among the most popular officials of all time. His outgoing personality and staunch work effort enabled him to travel the world. He devoted much of his life to recruiting, training and improving officials through his many papers and clinics. In a 33-year career that saw J. Dallas officiate more than 2,000 games, he served as a member of the Southern Conference, Atlantic Coast Conference, ECAC and Mason Dixon conference officiating staffs. His officiating legacy spanned numerous NIT and NCAA tournament games, as well as the international circuit. He referred a game that Kareem Abdul-Jabbar (then Lew Alcindor) played while in high school at Power Memorial in New York. A member of the NBA's first officiating crew, Shirley was the only American official chosen to work at the 1960 Olympic Games in Rome. A noted specialist in his field, Shirley has held a number of prestigious positions, including President of the IAABO (1952), the CBOA (1954) and the NABA. Knowledgeable in all aspects of the game, Shirley has conducted clinics in a dozen different countries. A true professional, Shirley is one of the most highly acclaimed officials by coaches, players and fellow officials. He was President and charter member of the College Basketball Officials Association (1955-56), a member of the NCAA Rules Committee, the chief official of the 1959 Pan American Games, a member of the U.S. Olympic Basketball Committee (1976) and Chairman of the U.S. Olympic Basketball Officials Committee (1976).
An oral history with Mr. Shirley also exists as part of MS0371, the Oral History Collection.
This note was written in 2005.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include plaques, scrapbooks, assorted carved figurines, trophies, pennants and patches, photographs and slides (including Hall of Fame, Red Auerbach), Rome Olympics files, media guides, officials manuals, Dallas Shirley's diploma, 1936 brick from the "Tin Tabernacle" gym, travel bags, clocks, and books and guides. The collection spans the 1950s through the 1980s.
Collection Organization
Organized in three series: Memorabilia, Slides and Photographs, Artifacts
Basketball; Black-and-white slides; Color slides; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Basketball Hall of Fame (Springfield, Mass.); George Washington University; Shirley, Dallas; National Collegiate Athletic Association; Olympic Games
- Memorabilia, 1950-1982; MS0217 Series 1; 15 Linear feet (Box 11, Box 10, Box 9, Box 8, Box 12, Box 19, Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of 19 boxes of Plaques, Scrapbooks, assorted carved figurines, trophies, ash trays, pennants and patches, photographs (including Hall of Fame, Red Auerbach, and Shirley referring a high school game with Lew Alcindor [Kareem Abdul-Jabbar]), Rome Olympics, clinics, books, basketball media guides, officials manuals, rule books, jackets and assorted hats, Shirley's GW diploma, 1936, brick from old "Tin Tabernacle" gym, 1981 Alumni Achievement Award, travel bags.
  - Memorabilia:Plaques, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Scrapbooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Plaques, award mugs, assorted carved figurines, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Plaques, trophies (small), ash trays, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Pennants and patches [should be re-housed], undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Photographs, including Hall of Fame, one with Red Auerbach, and Shirley referring a high school game with Lew Alcindor (Kareem Abdul-Jabbar), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Files, including Rome Olympics, clinics, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Books, basketball media guides, officials manuals, rule books, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Basketball official's jackets and assorted hats, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Books, including "Basketball Basic Skills for Coaches and Players" by Shirley (1962),mugs, and figurines, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Plaques, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Plaques, ash trays, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Books about basketball, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Shirley's GW diploma, 1936 and brick from "Tin Tabernacle", 1981 Alumni Achievement Award [fragile], undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Pillows and rubber stamp tree, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Travel bags, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Clocks, plaques, and figurines [broken glass], undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Misc. books and media guides, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia:Jacket and travel bags, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Slides and photographs, 1950-1982; MS0217 Series 2; 5 Linear feet (Box 20, Box 22, Box 21, Box 24, Box 23, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28)
  This series consists of 9 boxes of slides dealing with Dallas Shirley's travel, coaching and teaching basketball and the art of the referee.
  - Slides, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    General note
    Includes images from Shirley's travels to Puerto Rico. Slide cover labeled PR #5 is empty, tray is missing.
  - Slides, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Includes images from Shirley's travels Tunis and sports images.
  - Slides, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Includes images from Shirley's travels Tripoli, the International Fair,
  - Slides, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    Includes images from Shirley's travels New York, Jerusalem, Cairo, and Syria.
  - Slides, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Includes images from Shirley's travels Denmark, Athens, London, and Zurich.
  - Slides, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Includes images from Shirley's travels to Vienna, Munich, and Olympia.
  - Slides, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
    Includes images from Shirley's travels to Jamaica, Iceland, Italy, and Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Images, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Images, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
- Artifacts, 1962-1982; MS0217 Series 3; 4 Linear feet (Box 29)
  This series consists of 4 artifacts: a travel bag, an award, a large tray presented as a gift by the High Sport Committee of Tripolitainia, and a replica wood and stained glass case of Shirley's basketball Hall of Fame shrine.
  - Bag: "XX. Olympiade Munchen 1972 -- Award (in shape of basketball) with inscription "Appreciation award, National Association of Basketball Coaches presented to Dallas Shirley for his contributions to the game of basketball, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    Attached tag reads: "Your Participation is Appreciated Dallas Shirley Asst. to Commissioner. Lloyd Jordan Commissioner."
  - Award (in shape of basketball) with inscription "Appreciation award, National Association of Basketball Coaches presented to Dallas Shirley for his contributions to the game of basketball", 1975 (Object 30)
  - Large brass platter with Arabic decorative motifs. Inscribed in Arabic and English, "High Sport Committee Tripolitania -- Basket Ball Association 20/6 1962 -- Presented to J. Dallas Shirley Basketball Specialist -- In Appreciation of his Good Work in Tripoli", 1962 June 20 (Object 31)
  - Replica wood and stained glass case of Shirley's basketball Hall of Fame shrine, 1980 (Object 32)